[Music]
hey hey welcome to the final day of code
camp uh you made it to day five
congratulations
uh what we're going to be doing today is
something called kaleidoscope dessert
uh and as i kind of teased about
mckinley is going to be leading this one
uh so you're going to see her in just a
minute before i let her take the stage i
want to kind of review a couple things
we learned last time just because it's a
really good way to learn
so last time was the the catching dinner
uh we learned a lot of new skills and
that we learned
that you could use a command called
change the x by so you could actually
just change the x
which is the side to side and change the
y to go up and down
we learned that you could put code on
the stage so we had never put code on
the stage before but you have code that
you can put on each sprite
which is a good thing that you can do
but you can also put code on your stage
the stage is also sometimes called the
background
and what we did with that stage code is
we created clones
so cloning was really the big concept we
learned last time
and that's instead of having an
individual sprite down there
you have one sprite and then many clones
of it on your game it's a really
powerful concept
in programming we also did some more
things with
random numbers uh so hopefully you kind
of got some of those concepts uh down
today what we're doing is uh kind of
something completely different it's a
lightweight thing
it's kind of what i call like a half day
it's just meant to be a fun way to
finish our week
and so let me go ahead and start off by
clicking on this solution demo
and you can kind of see what we're up to
so to stick with our
dessert theme we made it kind of like as
though you're putting icing on the top
of a cake
but really it has almost nothing to do
with dessert
and the idea is is that you can ice the
top of a cake
i'm missing my background image here but
that's okay and so if i was putting
icing on a cake
i could decorate the top of my cake what
i'm doing here to do this and you'll see
when you
when you start doing it is i'm using the
arrow keys
so if i hit the up arrow i'm actually
controlling
three sprites at once so if i press
arrow that goes forwards
if i press arrow and right it kind of
like turns to the right some
um and the neat thing that you can do
here with a kaleidoscope
is you can make cool uh shapes and
patterns with it
so that's what we're up to uh so what i
want you to do
i'm supposed to say what we're going to
learn today as well but what i want you
to do
is go ahead and open up scratch.mit.edu
and create a new project and i am going
to get that far
done and then i'm going to turn it over
to mckinley
so mckinley you want to take the lead
from here
hi my name is mckinley fisher and i'm
going to be teaching
um today's lesson and so our campers
today
are mila bone
keegan and daddy
dave all right go ahead let's go ahead
and get started
so the first thing you need to do is
delete your cat sprite
after that you're going to go into the
cat on the sprite library to choose a
new sprite
the sprite you're going to choose is the
ball
once you get the ball it should look
like this
and then you can go into events
and get the green flagged so so far you
should have
your ball on your screen and green flag
in the code
after that you need to tell the ball
where to go
and that is found in motion
you need to drag over a go to x and y
block
and you change it to zero
zero so it'll be in the middle of the
screen
after that you um drag over a point and
direction block
right now it should have 90 in it
you're gonna change that 90 to zero
so so far your this is what your code
should look like along with your ball
after that you're going to go into
control and drag over
a forever loop
then you're going to drag over four
if statements once you do that you're
going to go into sensing
and drag over if he pressed
into those little boxes
so right now your code should look like
this uh when green flied
go to um x and y point and direction
a forever loop with four if statements
inside and inside this
if statements key space press
once you have that you're going to
change the spaces
to up arrow for the first if statement
down arrow for the second if statement
left for the third statement
and right for the fourth statement
once you do that or um you can go into
motion again so that um your ball will
actually move when you press these keys
for the up arrow you're going to drag
over a move
10 steps and you're going to
change that 10 steps to 3 steps
[Music]
and then you're going to drag over and
move 10 steps into the down
arrow and make
that 10 be a negative three steps
[Music]
once you do that you're going to get
into the turns for the
left arrow you are going to want to drag
this one over
which one's this one the lower
turn one
that has its arrow pointing left
and you're gonna change that 15 degrees
to five
and then once you do that you're going
to take the top term one
that's pointing right
and change that to five so right now
your code should have
um move or turn blocks
inside those if statements
[Music]
after that you're going to go into this
extension button
once you click on it your screen should
look like this
and you're going to see there's a lot of
different options
but the one we want is pen
once you do that you should see it opens
up an um
whole new block area that have
teal colored blocks once you do that
you're gonna grab um drag the first
command erase all
in between before the forever group for
before the forever loop and after the
point in direction zero
so your code should look like this
[Music]
and then um you're going to drag over a
stamp block and put it under the move
three
steps so now move your bottle and move
three steps and then
stamp and then
you're going to um for the down arrow
um this is optional you can do the same
thing
i'm going to um so that your ball makes
a line whenever it moves backwards
you don't have to do this it is
completely optional and up to you
once you do that you should be able to
move your ball around and it has a line
underneath it
and also if you would like your ball a
little faster you can change this move
three steps and move negative three
steps
[Music]
okay now that you have that um
you can duplicate this and how you do
that
is you click on the sprite and it should
show up with a duplicate and you're
going to hit that
so now you should have ball and ball too
right click yes
now there's it should be two balls
and now you do that one more time so
there is going to be
three balls duplicate so now you should
have
three balls on your screen
and now you can
change the balls colors if you would
like
to do that you go into ball
and then you click on costumes
you'll see it already has um a bunch of
different colored costumes
and you can choose whichever one you
would like but i'm going to choose blue
and also if you would like you can um
fill the ball of your own color
so now there's um and then you can do
the same for the
other balls so you click on the ball
then you click on its costumes
and choose a color you would like
once you do that um you'll see in the
code
for ball two and three it has the exact
same code
we want to um modify this code just a
bit
and so you're gonna change it so it says
one green flag to go to
x and y zero zero and then point in
direction
zero you want to change that zero to one
hundred
twenty
and then you're going to go into ball
three
and do almost the same thing except it's
going to be
a negative 120.
[Music]
once you do that and click the green
flag you should have
a kaleidoscope you made and you can um
have whatever colors you want and change
it
and um since it is cool
since it is kaleidoscope dessert we need
a background
which is going to be our cake
so you could draw your own but i'm going
to click on choose a background
and i'm going to choose a background
that i think looks like a cake
i like this heart i'm going to click on
it and now i'm going to have a heart
background
and um my balls kind of look like icing
so to do that your
project should look like this and now
you're going to give your project a name
i'm going to name mine kaleidoscope
okay um now that your project has a name
you can go
into file and hit save now
so now your project should be saved and
you're going to hit
share
in the instructions you can just tell
people to
use the arrow
arrow keys
and then there's also a url
you can share to your friends if you
would like
and so now let's see how our campers did
so now let's see how nina did can you
show us your project
whoa you're decorating your cake with
unicorns
great idea
okay now let's see how bowen did
i like your cake different colors
nice now let's see
how daddy did
he did his cake and he even gave one of
his balls a face
thank you now let's see how keaton did
very nice um this is one way to make it
i have um made an extension
extension i made i called it rainbow
worms
and so it looks like this
[Music]
and then you can move using this
and then you have a rainbow worm in the
middle that you activate with space and
then you use
wasd to move it
and so that is an extension you can
make and now i'm going to turn it back
over to daddy
[Music]
all right so that is the end folks uh
so uh kaleidoscope dessert was the final
thing that we wanted to teach you about
um we just kind of wanted to ramp up
camp a little bit and say a couple
things
the real take-home message from this
camp is coding is fun it's something you
can do you can totally do this
you'll see coding in your life just know
that it is something that you can handle
each day we work through a different app
or
project whatever you want to call it in
this camp we started with alphabet
breakfast where we worked on like
sprites and variables and flow control
day two was hedgehog snack where we did
some things with drawing and touching
color
day three was fish lunch it was the big
one where we did like movement control
and broadcasting events uh day four was
catching dinner where we learned about
clones and random numbers
uh and then day five was kaleidoscope
dessert
um each of these is just kind of meant
to teach you some different concepts let
you kind of get familiar with computer
science a little bit
if you want more there's a whole another
week of this camp
fair warning it is meant for an older
audience so some of those projects get
intense right
but if you wanted to give a shot we
certainly welcome having you there
but i wanted to say thanks for my whole
family for joining us
it's been a great camp week we hope that
you really liked it all right
see you next year bye
[Music]
you